"The Best Supplement to Prevent Skin Cancer"
Nicotinamide,
also known as niacinamide,
is a form of vitamin B3
that has been used topically
for decades
in the cosmetic field
to prevent skin aging,
as I've already covered.
So, researchers decided
to put it to the test orally
for skin cancer prevention.
In a petri dish,
skin samples taken
from breast reduction
and tummy tuck surgeries
exposed to UV
with or without niacinamide
found that it enhanced
DNA repair.
Would this translate out
into less cancer?
In a Phase II trial,
dozens of individuals
with four or more
precancerous actinic keratoses
each were randomized
to take a placebo
or 500 mg of niacinamide
once or twice a day.
Within two months,
there was a 35 percent reduction
in actinic keratoses
in the twice-a-day group,
and a 15 percent reduction
in the once-a-day group
compared to placebo.
It's not that they developed
fewer in those months,
but more
spontaneously disappeared
in the niacinamide groups.
What about actual cancers?
By month four, there were
five times fewer cancers
(11 placebo participants
developed 20 new skin cancers
versus only two
niacinamide participants
developing a total
of four new cancers).
Normally, it would be difficult
to fund studies
on nonpatentable products that
only cost a few cents a day,
but the results of this
and a similar study
on organ transplant patients
were so extraordinary
ONTRAC was born.
Oral Nicotinamide
to Reduce Actinic Cancer
was a publicly-funded
phase III trial
randomizing hundreds of people
with a personal history
of skin cancers
(actinic means UV-induced)
to 500 mg of nicotinamide
twice daily
or placebo for a full year.
By the end, there were
25 percent fewer cancers
with no significant
side effects
for just pennies a day.
You have to keep it up, though.
At a six-month follow-up
after the study was over,
the cancer rates equalized back
to baseline rates.
What are the downsides?
A study of 500 people
put on up to three grams
of niacinamide a day
for five years (trying
to prevent type 1 diabetes)
unearthed no adverse effects
over placebo
(though it failed to prevent
type 1 diabetes).
The high tolerance
of niacinamide
is partly due
to its water-soluble nature,
such that you just pee out
any excess.
But those with end-stage
kidney failure on dialysis
don't have functioning kidneys,
and so, blood levels
should be monitored,
as, in that context,
niacinamide can cause
a serious, though reversible,
drop in platelets,
which are important
for blood clotting.
High enough doses may become
toxic to the liver, though,
even with normal kidneys.
Vasodilatory side effects,
like facial flushing,
attributed to niacinamide
in some older studies
were likely due
to a less purified form
contaminated with
residual niacin.
(I know it's confusing!
Niacin, also known
as nicotinic acid,
is the precursor of,
but very different from,
niacinamide, which is
synonymous with nicotinamide.)
One concern
regarding any treatment
for a largely lifestyle disease
is that individuals may neglect
other defensive measures,
overconfident in
the supplement's protection.
Regarding drug interactions,
a concern has been raised
about taking niacinamide
together with carbamazepine,
a popular anti-seizure drug
(sold as Tegretol).
But, in general,
as the ONTRAC researchers
concluded,
"Oral nicotinamide
is safe and effective
in reducing the rates
of new nonmelanoma skin cancers
and precancerous growths
in high-risk patients."
To their credit, a 2021 survey
of skin cancer surgeons found
that three-quarters
recommended its use.
Other than nicotinamide,
how else might we protect
against skin cancer
from the inside out?
That's what I'll cover next.